The ZOS provides ZOS UNIX file support into native ISPF edit and browse functions.
The panels are modified so that the other dataset name field is a scrollable field which
accepts ZOS UNIX path name of up to 1,023 characters in length.
ISPF assumes the ZOS UNIX path name is entered in this field when the first character is
a foreslash, a tilde, a dot or two dots.
A ZOS UNIX directory selection list is displayed when the path name for a directory is specified
on any of the following, the view and edit entry panels, a call to browse edit and view
services, the edit and view move copy browse edit and view primary commands or the browse
edit view and browse commands.
The directory selection list is almost identical to the list displayed from the ZOS UNIX directory
list utility.
The selection list supports the S for select line command allowing you to select the file
to be processed with the function, for example edit that info list.
The view entry panel displayed by using ISPF option one is changed to allow a ZOS UNIX file
path name to be entered in the other dataset name field.
Also the new record length field is added to allow a record length to be specified when
browsing a ZOS UNIX file.
The value entered in this field is used by ISPF to display the data in the file as a
fixed length record rather than using the new line character to delimit each record.
This is useful for browsing files which would otherwise have very large records if
the new line character is used as the record delimiter.
On the edit entry panel the record length field has a slightly different effect than
on the view entry panel.
With edit ISPF normally treats ZOS UNIX files as having variable length records.
The record length field on the edit entry panel allows you to specify a record length
which ISPF edit will use to load the records from the file into the edit session as fixed
length records.
When the file is saved it's saved with fixed length records.
So the record length field allows you to convert a variable length record file into
a fixed length records file.
On screen we see the difference between browsing a ZOS UNIX file without specifying a record
length and browsing a ZOS UNIX file with a record length of 40 specified.
The edit entry panel displayed using ISPF option 2 is changed to allow a ZOS UNIX file
path name to be entered in the other dataset name field.
Also the new record length field is added to allow a record length to be specified
when editing a ZOS UNIX file.
The following ISPF edit primary and macro commands support the specification of a ZOS UNIX path
name as an operand.
Those are compare, copy, create, move and replace.
A path name can be specified in the format accepted as input in the other dataset name
field.
Also if editing a ZOS UNIX file when these commands are used a plus sign can be specified
as the first character of the path name to represent the path name of the directory containing
the file being edited.
Let's take a look at a few examples.
The copy command can now be used to copy data from a ZOS UNIX file into the data being
edited.
This is done by specifying the path name for the ZOS UNIX regular file as a parameter with
the copy command or specifying the path name on the edit copy panel displayed when no data
source is specified with the copy command.
If the path name for a directory is specified a directory selection list is displayed allowing
you to select the regular file to be copied.
The move command can now be used to move data from a ZOS UNIX file into the data
being edited and it works in much the same way as copy by specifying the path name
for the ZOS UNIX regular file as a parameter with the move command or specifying the path
name on the edit move panel displayed when no data source is specified with the move
command.
Keep in mind here that the ZOS UNIX regular file is deleted after the data is moved.
ISPF personal dataset lists are enhanced to support the saving and retrieval of ZOS UNIX
file name paths.
Retrieval of path names is supported on those ISPF edit, view and browse panels that allow
a path name to be entered in the other dataset name field.
Retrieval of path names is also supported on the ZOS UNIX directory list entry panel.
The nretrieve command also supports the automatic retrieval of path names on those panels that
allow ZOS UNIX path names to be specified.
ISPF personal dataset lists support saving and retrieving ZOS UNIX file path names.
Users can now add UNIX style path names manually to their personal dataset lists.
Personal dataset lists are a good way to group, for example by project, datasets and
ZOS UNIX file path names that you use frequently.
You can use personal dataset lists to avoid typing in dataset names and ZOS UNIX file
path names and to create customized dataset lists similar to those using ISPF option 3.4.
Still with me?
We've covered a lot in this series of videos.
We're going to switch gears from here on in and start to look at recommendations for
file system structure, backup and recovery and use of the network file system.
That's coming up next.